טוב tov today's דף daf is מ"א. Mem Aleph. We're a bit
behind, we pick up on מ"ם עמוד ב', Mem Amud Bet, about
six lines from the top. אם היה שמן מזוקק איני מוציא לו
שמרים. Im haya shemen mezukkak eini motzi lo shmarim. This is talking
about if somebody is watching stuff, how much and it's fruit or
it's wine or it's oil, how much can he assume gets sort
of eaten by the rats or absorbed by the vessels? So he
doesn't have to return the full amount that he received. And then
it says similar discussions about if you're selling something, then how much
sort of can you assume that there's going to be a lees
by the, by the, by the wine and so on. So it
says that if it was, if the person entrusted to him
pure oil without any of the dross or without any of the
lees or whatever, then he does not get to deduct when he
returns it the dross that settled at the bottom because there is
no dross. So the גמרא Gemara says והא אי אפשר דלא בלע.
v'ha i efshar d'lo bala. So and then I'm sorry, and then
it says וכולי, v'chulei, וכולי v'chulei is an important word here, because
then it's really going on the second part of the משנה Mishnah
that says that if the vessels that they were stored in
had already absorbed wine or oil, then he has to return the
full amount. He can't deduct the amount that was presumably absorbed by
the walls of the vessel because the vessels had already fully absorbed.
So the גמרא Gemara doesn't believe that this is true, that the
vessel fully absorbed and not be able to take in any more.
So the גמרא Gemara says והא אי אפשר דלא בלע. v'ha i
efshar d'lo bala. It's impossible that they are not going to absorb
something. אמר רב נחמן Amar Rav Nachman במזופפים שנו. b'mizufafim shanu. We're
not talking about just that it's old, we're talking about it's a
combination that it's old and that they are plastered on the interior.
And the combination of that too will prevent them from absorbing any
more. אביי אמר Abaye amar אפילו תימא שלא
במזופפים, afilu teima shelo b'mizufafim, even if that's not the case, כיון
דטען טען, keivan d't'on t'on, yeah, what the משנה Mishnah is saying
is right. Once it is like, you know, beladen, it's beladen. Once
it's carrying all that oil in the walls, it's not going to
absorb any more. All right. רבי יהודה אומר אף המוכר שמן מזוקק
לחבירו כל ימות השנה הרי זה מקבל עליו לוג ומחצה שמרים למאה.
Rabbi Yehuda omer af hamocher shemen mezukkak l'chavero kol yemot hashana harei
zeh mekabbel alav log u'mechet shmarim l'mea. If somebody agrees to sell
pure oil to somebody, Michael, I'm going to sell you, you know,
a gallon of pure oil, you'll give me $10 for it now,
you'll come in, you'll take it little by little, I'll keep a
running track, right? Okay, so when I say a gallon and then
but a gallon but I really don't have to give you a
gallon. I really get to give you, you know,
this לוג, log, it was a סאה, se'ah, right? No, for 100
לוג, log, I get to deduct one and a half percent because
since basically if you had bought the whole thing, you would have
gotten one and a half percent שמרים shmarim of the lees. So
when I'm selling it to you and I'm giving it little by
little, I'm agreeing to give you out the pure stuff, but it's
understood that I'm only giving you 98 and a half percent of
the amount agreed upon because you would have if you had bought
the whole thing at once, you would have gotten one and a
half percent of the שמרים shmarim of the sort of the, you
know,
the pulp, whatever it's called. Anyway, of the lees.
You buy the whole well
you
buy like a liter, do you get that proportionally?
Yeah, I mean that's the funny thing. The funny thing about the
no, I presumably you do do it proportionally, but the funny thing
about it is, what do you mean? We said a gallon of
pure oil for this price. So that meant the full gallon. So
somehow like there's some understanding that, you know, if you had get
it off my shelf, you would have gotten it wouldn't have been
100%, it wouldn't have been pure virgin olive oil, it would have
just been olive oil with the lees, and I'm charging the same
price, but you don't have the money and you can't use it
all at once. So somehow there's that understanding that since that's what
you would have gotten if you would have bought the whole thing
and walked home with it, then when you buy it little by
little and I give it out to you, when you buy it
and I give it out to you little by little, that you
don't, you know, you don't get a better deal off of it.
If anything, I should be charging more for that.
If you're buying from, you know, the small producer exactly.
Right. I understand. Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. אמר
אביי, Amar Abaye, so what we're going to try to figure out
is why the rabbis disagree, okay? Maybe this will help clarify it,
maybe not. אמר אביי Amar Abaye ולכשתמצא לומר u'le'chashtam tzalomar לדברי רבי
יהודה מותר לערבב שמרים l'divrei Rabbi Yehuda muttar l'arvei shmarim ולדברי חכמים
אסור לערבב שמרים. u'le'divrei chachamim assur l'arvei shmarim. According to רבי יהודה,
Rabbi Yehuda, if you're buying, let's say, a large amount in general,
you would be and you, you know, you would be permissible as
the store owner to mix up into it all of the lees
and to sell it non-pure. And according to the חכמים, chachamim, you
would not be allowed. And this how does that figure out? לדברי
רבי יהודה מותר לערבב שמרים l'divrei Rabbi Yehuda muttar l'arvei shmarim והיינו
טעמא דמקבל, v'hainu taama d'mekabbel, this is דאמר ליה, d'amar lei, and
this is the reason why you have to, you, the buyer, have
to accept the fact that I'm not going to give you that
I'm going to only give you 98 and a half percent of
pure. דאמר ליה, d'amar lei, because I say to you אי בעי
לערבויי לך מי לא ערבויי לך? ei baei l'arvuye lach mi lo
arvaye lach? Look,
even though you said you're buying pure, I really am entitled to
mix up the dross with it. Okay, so then you would have
gotten your 100 with the dross. Okay, so now
too, take the, you know, 98 and a half percent of it
in pure oil and take another one and a half percent, here's
just some dross and some lees, and do with it whatever you
want. Okay, so that's very reasonable because I could have sold it
to you all mixed up
together and ולימא
ליה l'eima lei wait one minute, but let's Can't the purchaser say
to him, אי ערבת ליה, ei arvat leih, הוי מזדבן ליה, havi
mizdaben leih, if you had mixed it up or kept it mixed
up and sold it to me with the dross in it, then
I could go ahead and resell it to the next guy and
I would have a hundred units to resell. השתא מאי עבד ליה
לחודיה ולא מזדבן, hashta mai avat leih lachudeih velo mizdaben,
what am I going to do with one and a half units
of dross? Nobody wants to buy dross. So I only have ninety-eight
and a half units to sell, so I actually that doesn't do
me any good. Assuming that the guy who's buying it is actually
a reseller, right? So therefore he says, I actually preferred it all
mixed up because that allows me to sell it as a hundred
units. And by you separating it, it actually hurt my ability to
resell the full amount. So the Gemara says, no, בבעל הבית עסקינן,
bevaal habayit askinan, no we're not talking about a reseller, we're talking
about a homeowner, דניחא ליה בצילא, denicha leih betzilla, that he wants
to get the pure oil. So I actually did him a favor.
I could have given you a hundred units mixed up, you would
rather have had the dross removed. So fine, so you're going to
get ninety-eight and a half units with the dross removed. ולימא ליה,
v'leima leih, why doesn't the homeowner say to him, מדלא ערבת לי
אחולי אחלת לי, midelo arvat li acholei achalta li, wait one minute,
you're right, you could have, but you chose to be a nice
guy, you chose to give it to me pure, so what you're
basically doing, I'll read that as an implicit מחילה. mechila. I'll read
that as basically saying you're prepared to give me the hundred units
as pure oil. Okay? That's how I'm going to interpret it. If
you would have, you would have been in your right, but instead
you decided to give it to me pure, so fine but we
still agreed to a hundred units. Very reasonable question. I learned this
the hard way many years ago that in, it never pays to
be a nice guy. Like we moved into an apartment many years
ago when we were in Florida, and we were in Boca for
two years or so. And something about I don't know the landowner
or whatever, the owner of the apartment, there was some problem with
it, I forget what, something with the ceiling and the fixture and
this and that, landlord, thank you, some problem with it, and like
we just figured ach it's so not worth the effort whatever like
and then finally like six months later we decided to complain about
it and the guy's like you're right, right, if you had a
legitimate, the fact that you didn't make your complaint earlier means you
basically waived your right. So like, okay, that was a real lesson.
You don't win by being a nice guy in terms of these
things. Then we're just going to interpret it as a waiving of
rights. So that is if you wanted to fine, but you didn't,
you gave it to me clean, so you have to give me
still a hundred units. Okay. Okay. So the Gemara says so why
don't we say that? Why do we say that you're still entitled
to give him the one and a half units of the dross?
So the Gemara says רבי יהודה לטעמיה, Rabbi Yehuda letaameih, Rabbi Yehuda
goes to his reasoning, דלית ליה מחילה, deleis leih mechila, he doesn't
hold that we read things as מחילה. mechila. He sort of holds
that we assume things based on the price that you paid and
we're going to interpret things to be consistent with that. דתנן, detnan,
standard market,
right, right. דתנן, detnan, מכר לו את הצמד לא מכר לו את
הבקר, machar lo es hatzemed lo machar lo es habakar, if you
have a transaction and you say to a guy I'm going to
buy the yoke. Okay. So obviously and you pay him whatever then
the words the yoke doesn't mean that you used to yoke two
oxen together, means only the yoke, not the cattle. מכר לו את
הבקר לא מכר לו את הצמד, machar lo es habakar lo machar
lo es hatzemed, which is pretty obvious I guess, but if you
sold him the two cattle you also didn't include the yoke in
the deal. Fine. רבי יהודה אומר הדמים מודיעים, Rabbi Yehuda omer hadamim
modiyim, Rabbi Yehuda said whoa whoa wait, you have to also look
at the things. You have to look at the amount of money
paid. כיצד, keitzad, אמר לו מכור לי צמדך במאתים זוז, amar lo
m'chor li tzimdecha b'masayim zuz, somebody says sell me your yoke for
two hundred zuz, like sell me your yoke for ten thousand dollars.
Okay, deal. Okay. So clearly the word yoke meant the two cattle
yoked together. It did not mean the yoke. Right. So הדבר ידוע
שאין הצמד במאתים זוז, hadavar ידוע she'ein hatzemed b'masayim zuz, nobody pays
two hundred zuz for a lousy yoke. Clearly he meant the two
cattle yoked together, oxen. Thank you. וחכמים אומרים אין הדמים ראיה, v'chachamim
omrim ein hadamim raya, no,
it's not a proof. Okay. So therefore we just look
at the times he trusted yoke,
just know what you wanted. Okay. So because of Rabbi Yehuda, Rabbi
Yehuda basically says you look at the money. So now that's obviously
in a case where the money is like a great disparity. You
would think the difference between paying for ninety-eight and a half units
and a hundred units is not a big deal and then maybe
we would read מחילה. mechila. But the Gemara's never saying no, it's
still saying no, the price for the hundred units with the dross
was whatever. If you're giving him ninety-eight and a half units, we
interpret that as we don't interpret that as מחילה, mechila, we interpret
that as going to be consistent with the price. So you're still
entitled to give and the חכמים Chachamim would disagree on this point
and you would be entitled to give ninety-eight and a half units
of pure oil with one and a half units of the dross.
Okay. וחכמים אומרים אין הדמים ראיה. v'chachamim omrim ein hadamim raya. Okay.
So the Gemara says ולדברי חכמים אסור לערב שמרים, u'lidvrei chachamim assur
l'arev shemarim,
and for the חכמים, Chachamim, you're not allowed to mix up the
dross. והיינו טעמא דלא מקבל, vehainu taama d'lo mekabel, and that's why
the guy is entitled to say I refuse to accept the dross,
you have to give me a hundred pure units. דאמר ליה, de'amar
leih, אי בעית לערבויי מי הוה שרי לך, ei bayit le'arvuyei mi
hava sharei lach, if you had wanted even to sell me the
whole amount with the dross, you would not be allowed. השתא נמי
לא מקבלינא, hashta nami lo m'kabelina, so here too when I said
a hundred units, I meant a hundred units of clean oil.
Okay, that seems to be a pretty reasonable way of framing the
debate, that the question is if I would have sold it to
you with the large amount all at once, would I have been
able to sell it to you with the dross? So if the
answer is yes, then I’m only going to give you ninety-eight and
a half units that have been filtered. If the answer is no,
I would then of course have to give you a hundred units
that are filtered.
Buying a large amount. I’m buying a cup of oil from you,
you can't give me any percent of dross.
Nah, that's maybe. I mean I know, it's possible, it's not spelled
out. אמר ליה רב פפא לאביי. Amlei Rav Pappa le'Abaye. אדרבה, Addereba,
the opposite is, איפכא מסתברא, Ipkha misstabra, the opposite makes sense. לדברי
חכמים מותר לערבוי שמורים. Le'divrei hachamim mutar le'arvui shemarim. According to the
חכמים, hachamim, if you had sold a large amount you're generally allowed
to mix it up. Okay, to mix up with the dross. So
therefore if that's true, why here do you have to give him
a hundred pure units? והיינו טעמא דלא מקבל, Vehaino ta'ama de'lo mekabel,
here's why the guy does not have to accept one and a
half units of dross, דאמר ליה, damar lei, מנה לא עבדת לי
אחלית לי. minlo avdat li achliit li. Yeah, you could have, you
were entitled to sell me a hundred units with the dross. You
chose to sell me pure units. Okay, so you implicitly were מוחל
mocheil your right to sell it to me with the dross. So
therefore כי פרסאי, kiparsai, so you have to give me a hundred
units. Okay, we look at what you did. ולדברי רבי יהודה אסור
לערבוי שמורים. U'ledivrei Rabbi Yehuda assur le'arvui shemarim. According to רבי יהודה,
Rabbi Yehuda, you're forbidden. So if you're forbidden, then why don't you
have to sell a hundred clean units? והיינו טעמא דמקבל, Vehaino ta'ama
de'mekabel, here's why the guy has to accept one and a half
units of the dross, דאמר ליה, damar lei, איבעו לארבויי ולא שרי
לי, iba'u la'arvui v'lo shari li, לארבויי לך. la'arvui lach.
If I would have wanted, I the storeowner say, if I would
have wanted to sell you with the dross, I'm not allowed. סו
קיבולי לא מקבלת, So kibulai lo mekabelat, you wouldn't have accepted it.
So you therefore so if you're not going to accept that, meaning
you're just going to accept, you know, the only thing I can
do is sell you a hundred pure units. If that's true, without
sort of at least, you know, ninety-eight and a half because of
the dross, because of you know the dross which I'm not allowed
to do, I have to sell I can't sell you with the
dross. זבין דזבין תגרא איקרי? Zavin de'zavin tigra ikri? Somebody who buys
and sells at the same price, you call that guy a merchant?
Right, so where's my profit margin? Okay, so now the funniest thing
is, what do you mean what's your profit margin? Maybe you know,
you just raise the price from what you bought it at. תוספות
Tosafos says for whatever reason we have to assume that the scenario
is, I don't know why, that the profit margin I make is
basically by, you know, somehow I buy a hundred and I sell
it at the same price I bought it for but I only
sell like the ninety-eight and a half. And I make the profit
margin by not selling the hundred pure units of course, you know,
so...
Yeah,
right, so somehow it has to be his leave. Yeah,
right, so I don't know, somehow that the profit margin is the
fact that I whatever I that I sell maybe again. No, no,
I don't think so. But somehow the idea is I'm sorry let's
look at תוספות Tosafos because I really don't understand it too. If
you look at תוספות, Tosafos, זבין דזבין תגרא איקרי, zavin de'zavin tigra
ikri, מאי שלא היה מוצא למכור ביוקר יותר משלקח. ma'i she'lo haya
motzi limkor biyokar yoser mishe'lakach. You somehow you can't buy it more
than you sell it for. Or you can't sell for more than
you buy for. וכך אמר ליה אדעתא דהכי קניתי ממך שידעתי שאעכב
לו גמכסא כדי שארויח קצת, V'kach amar lei ada'ta d'hachi kaniti mimach
she'eida she'a'akiv lo gamachsa kedei she'arviach ktzat, that I hold back, you
know, one and a half in order to but if but if
you're selling it pure and you're holding back one and a half
of the lees, I don't know how much profit you're making, you
know. Maybe what you do is...
I'm wondering a minute before, yesterday.
Right, I don't know, maybe what you're doing is that you're buying
a hundred units of filtered and when you're selling it, you're selling
only ninety-eight and a half units of filtered. And that's your profit.
But the reason you're entitled to sell ninety-eight and a half is
because you say it's like a hundred units because that what a
hundred units would be if it had the dross in it. I
don't really get it. It's quite funny because, you know, it's very
nice that you're not making any profit, but like what's the verbal
agreement? If the verbal agreement is a hundred units for this price
and the הלכה halakha is that you have to sell pure olive
oil, you're not allowed to sell filtered olive oil, it's like so
you said a hundred units, a hundred units meant filtered and I
mean, you know, it meant pure and not you know, if you
have to sell pure and not with the dross. So and you
said a hundred units, so it meant a hundred units of pure.
So I really don't understand it. All right, anyway, that's the point.
That somehow it's implicit that a hundred units doesn't mean a hundred
full units, it means a hundred units what that would be given
the reality that you're not allowed to sell it with the dross,
which is ninety-eight and a half.
All right, the opposite of that case where you go into the
שוק shuk and then they like top it off with like one
little extra half of a...
Yeah, we're going to get to that. We haven't seen that yet,
but that's true. Okay, תנא אחד הלוקח ואחד המפקיד לפתיתין. Tana echad
haloke'ach v'echad hamafkid l'ptitin. When the same הלכה halakha applies to the
purchaser or to the one who is keeping the grain, right, because
they're both the point about when how much can you deduct when
you sell it to the person or when you return it to
the person? It's like the you know, the dross or the amount
that gets absorbed or whatever. So they have the same הלכה halakha
when it comes to the פתיתין. ptitin. What are the פתיתין? ptitin?
So רש"י Rashi says that it is the like the the dirt
or the you know, the dross that comes from the seeds, not
the seeds themselves per se apparently because we spoke about the שמרים
shemarim already when you come to selling oil. Okay, so it's like
creates cloudy oil as opposed to before we talked directly about the
seeds themselves. So what does this mean? מאי פתיתין, Mai ptitin, אילימא
כי היכא דלוקח לא מקבל פתיתין מפקיד נמי לא מקבל פתיתין, ee-leima
keicha deloke'ach lo mekabel ptitin mafkid nami lo mekabel ptitin,
if it means similar to this discussion before about the wine or
whatever or the oil that the same way the purchaser does not
have to accept the dross according to I guess the חכמים. chachamim.
So therefore If you're keeping the oil you don't get to deduct
you know this you know this dross or whatever. So the גמרא
Gemara says ולימא ליה פטקיטיך
מאי עביד להו? Uleima lei pitkatcha mai avid lehu? So so what
does it mean because why can't you basically say to him what
am I supposed to do you know with this dross? So
okay so the גמרא Gemara says one minute one minute כי היכי
דלוקח לא מקבל פטקיטין מפקיד נמי לא
מקבל פטקיטין ולימא ליה פטקיטיך
מאי עביד להו. Ke'heichei delokeach lo mekabel pitkatim mafkid nami lo mekabel
pitkatim uleima lei pitkatcha
mai avid lehu.
Right
what am I supposed to do with your right meaning the basic
point being like why do I have to remove your פטקיטין pitkatim
and return it to you you know the stuff like you know
hold on I'm not sure I'm getting this one minute. אלא כי
היכי דמפקיד מקבל פטקיטין לוקח נמי מקבל פטקיטין. Ela ki heichei demafkid
mekabel pitkatim lokeach nami mekabel pitkatim. I mean
I
don't exactly
understand the words of the גמרא Gemara but I think it's basically
the same point of the משנה Mishnah which the same point of
the משנה Mishnah is is that you're always entitled to give back
the amount minus sort of the dross. So here too right if
you're the person watching the object right you always give it back
minus the dross so here also why should you not be entitled
to give it back minus the dross except I just don't exactly
how to fit into the words you know what am I supposed
to do with your dross. But anyway אלא כי היכי דמפקיד מקבל
פטקיטין לוקח נמי מקבל פטקיטין. Ela ki heichei demafkid mekabel pitkatim lokeach
nami mekabel pitkatim. The same way in the normal case of the
מפקיד mafkid basically you know you the owner have to accept you're
getting it back you have to accept that it's sort of minus
the dross. So לוקח נמי מקבל פטקיטין. Lokeach nami mekabel pitkatim. So
therefore when you purchase it you have to accept that you're getting
you know you're getting it minus as it were the dross. So
similar to the discussion before that you're getting it minus the שמרים
shmarim at least according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda I get to
hold back the amount that it would sort of of the שמרים
shmarim here too you get to hold it back.
It makes sense like if I'm giving you my oil to watch
and you're going to give it back to me I can't say
like I gave you the scum when I gave whatever
you give it back to me without the scum.
Give it back to me without it don't get to like make
money off it.
Exactly exactly I just didn't understand the exact phrasing of what am
I supposed to do with the scum but yes that's the point
you give it back to me clean and it's minus the amount
of the scum. That's what we've seen consistently
about the פקדון pikadon that you know obviously if that's the amount
that's sort of not being returned I reduce that amount but the
question is in the case of the purchase. So the גמרא Gemara
says אלא כי היכי דמפקיד מקבל פטקיטין לוקח נמי מקבל פטקיטין. Ela
ki heichei demafkid mekabel pitkatim lokeach nami mekabel pitkatim. The same way
in the מפקיד mafkid of course if you give it to me
and I return it to you minus the scum then I don't
have to give you the extra amount of the volume of the
scum. So here too in a case of a purchase if you
buy 100 units then there's one unit of the scum then I
really only need to give you 99 units. Okay so it's similar
to the discussion before about the שמרים. shmarim. So the גמרא Gemara
says ומי מקבל לוקח פטקיטין? Umi mekabel lokeach pitkatim? Is that really
true that you have to accept that? והתניא רבי יהודה אומר לא
אמרו שמן עכור אלא למוכר בלבד שהרי לוקח מקבל עליו לוג ומחצה
שמרים בלא פטקיטין. Vehatanya Rabbi Yehuda omer lo amru shemen achor ela
lemocher bilvad sheharei lokeach mekabel alav log umachetza shmarim belo pitkatim.
So basically when you said this idea
about cloudy oil so the loss of that cloudiness you know has
to be absorbed by the seller. Because when we said that you
know the לוקח lokeach takes you know רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda own
position that said that if I buy 100 units I have to
take 98 and a half of clean minus one and a half
of the שמרים shmarim he basically says okay so the purchaser as
it were takes the loss of the one and a half שמרים.
shmarim. Okay he gets the 98 and a half units not 100
units. But the seller doesn't get to deduct more for the cloudiness
of the oil. All right so that's how it read I don't
know ואמרו בשמן עכור אלא למוכר
בלבד Veamru be-shemen achor ela lemocher bilvad it's only the seller absorbs
that loss שהרי לוקח מקבל עליו לוג ומחצה שמרים בלא פטקיטין sheharei
lokeach mekabel alav log umachetza shmarim belo pitkatim that minus one and
a half includes the assumption of that it's going to be clean
not just not going to have the שמרים shmarim there but not
have the cloudiness there.
So some take a loss. What? Yeah the- actually don't take a
loss because he will have pure oil.
Right
that's the funny thing right like yeah I don't understand this at
all like why doesn't the market just adjust
for this when it comes out fresh fresh stays for a couple
of days and then it settles right
and then it settles right goes to the bottom of the vessel.
Aha aha right.
So okay
so so that's so once that separates is exactly sort of what
we're dealing with. But the point is that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
is saying that one and a half units includes the the dross
here I mean includes the cloudiness.
So the גמרא Gemara says לא קשיא. Lo kashya. Anyway I don't
get this obviously 100 percent. הא דיהיב ליה זוזי בתשרי וקשקיל מיניה
בניסן. Ha deyehiv lei zuzei beTishrei vekashakil minei beNissan. I guess it's
very cute okay. Did he pay for the money in תשרי Tishrei
and then he's taking it in ניסן Nisan כי מידי דתשרי Ki
middei de-Tishrei based on the amount that that money would have bought
in תשרי, Tishrei, okay? In תשרי Tishrei the prices are lower. So
if you pay me for the what? That's the time of the
harvest, etc. I yeah, exactly. So and רש"י Rashi says some other
reason I think.
No, by ניסן Nisan already, since it's the time of the harvest,
the stuff is cloudier. And by ניסן Nisan presumably by then people
have filtered it or as Joe was saying, the stuff has separated
naturally or whatever. Okay, so therefore the prices are lower in תשרי.
Tishrei. Lower, the prices in תשרי Tishrei more reflect the reality that
the stuff is cloudy and has the שמרים shmarim and so on.
So if I pay the תשרי Tishrei prices and I get it
in ניסן, Nisan, so כי מידי דתשרי ki middei de-Tishrei based on
the prices, you know, based on the amount that the money would
have bought me in תשרי, Tishrei, so then obviously so then the
seller gets the right to hold back, you know, that
amount. האי דיהבי זוזי בניסן וקשקיל מיני בניסן כי מידי דניסן. Hai
de-yahvei zuzei be-Nisan ve-ka-shakal minei be-Nisan ki middei de-Nisan. But if I
pay ניסן Nisan prices and I'm getting it in ניסן, Nisan, then
the prices basically reflect the reality that I'm getting filtered one and
not unfiltered one. So thankfully the גמרא Gemara finally here sort of
says, look, what are you buying? Are you buying unfiltered wine, are
you buying filtered wine? If you're buying filtered wine and the guy
is selling, you know, then he doesn't have a right to not
give you the full number of units. If you're buying unfiltered wine
maybe he does. Why this only becomes an issue with the cloudiness
and not with the שמרים, shmarim, I don't know. So I don't
really fully get this. Yes, Joe?
Maybe this is oversimplifying. If
you go to the grocery store, you want to buy vegetables. You
want to buy a pound of beets at a certain, even though
the greens, let's say, are useless.
Right, right, but in a rational market, they charge a different amount
if you buy the Portobello caps as opposed to if you buy
the whole Portobello, they charge more per pound. Right? So all right,
exactly. So let the market adjust here. I don't really understand this.
All right, let's keep on going. Okay. המפקיד חבית אצל חבירו ולא
ייחדו לו בעלים מקום. Ha-mafkid chavit etzel chaveiro ve-lo yichadu lo be-alim
makom. Now we're thankfully switching gears to something that's a little more
conceptual and a little less understanding about the markets in ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael or בבל. Bavel. Okay. המפקיד חבית אצל חבירו ולא ייחדו
לו בעלים מקום. Ha-mafkid chavit etzel chaveiro ve-lo yichadu lo be-alim makom.
So I go ahead and I put my barrel of wine or
oil, whatever, at Michael's house. Michael, watch this barrel for me. And
I don't tell you we're going to keep it right here in
this corner of your basement. Put it wherever you want. Okay. וטלטלה
ונשתברה. Ve-tiltelah ve-nishtabrah.
And Michael is moving it around at some point and it breaks.
אם מתוך ידו נשברה. Im mitokh yado nishberah.
Now let's see if it broke while he was still handling it.
לצרכו חייב. Letzorkho chayav. If he's moving it for his own convenience,
okay, which could mean a couple of things. Could mean he wants
to steal it, wants to sit on it. It's in the way,
he's got to move it around, he's got to move some furniture,
okay, something sort of serving his needs, then he's חייב. chayav. לצרכה
פטור. Letzorkhah patur. If he's moving it for its own sake, to
protect it, you know, or some other reason, then he's doing his
job of a שומר, shomer, he's פטור. patur. So לצרכו letzorkho somehow
is considered... well, לצרכה letzorkhah is not פשיעה, pshia, לצרכה letzorkhah is
taking care of it. לצרכו letzorkho when Michael is doing it for
his own needs, that somehow makes him as we'll see—makes him a
גנב, ganav, a גזלן, gazlan, does it make him a שליח יד,
sholei'ach yad, does it make him a שואל שלא ברשות? sho'el she-lo
bi-reshut? It does something, okay, for him. Maybe the example I gave
of לצרכו letzorkho that he just wants to get it out of
the way for furniture is not the best example. לצרכו letzorkho probably
has a better sense of he wants to somehow use it for
himself. We'll see more in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay. אם משהניחה נשברה.
Im mishe-hinichah nishberah.
But if after he put it back down it broke, בין לצרכו
בין לצרכה פטור. bein letzorkho bein letzorkhah patur.
Whatever liability he had because he was using it for his own
needs, if he returns it, then he is done. He's returned the
object to the owners. Now that's when it didn't have a particular
place. ייחדו לו בעלים מקום. Yichadu lo be-alim makom. If the owners
designated a particular place וטלטלה ונשתברה ve-tiltelah ve-nishtabrah and then he moved
it, בין מתוך ידו בין משהניחה, bein mitokh yado bein mishe-hinichah,
whether he's still handling it or whether he put it back, לצרכו
חייב לצרכה פטור. letzorkho chayav letzorkhah patur. Clearly again, if he's moving
it for its own needs, that's the job of a שומר. shomer.
But if he somehow is taking it for his needs, so he's
to some degree a גזלן gazlan again, we'll see more about this
in the גמרא, Gemara, taking my object for his own needs. And
putting it back does is not considered returning it to the owner.
Now that's a little strange. Why isn't putting it back—if you put
it back without there being a specific place it's returning it, putting
it back with a specific place should surely be returning it. I'm
going to ruin the suspense and tell you that the גמרא Gemara
is going to say that the reason you're פטור patur in the
second case is because you didn't put it back in the same
place. If you put it back in the same place, what?
You're
חייב chayav because you didn't put it back in the same place.
If you had put it back in the same place, then you
actually would be פטור, patur, it would be like the first case
of the משנה, Mishnah, you would have returned it to the owners.
All right, let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. הא מני
רבי ישמעאל היא. Ha manni? Rebbe Yishmael hi. Who is the first
part of the משנה Mishnah that says once you let go of
it, once you put it back, you know, or put it down,
you're פטור, patur, is רבי ישמעאל. Rebbe Yishmael. דאמר לא בעינן דעת
בעלים. De-amar lo be'inan da'at be-alim.
You don't need the owners to be aware when you've returned an
object that you've stolen from them. You just return it and you're
exempt from your obligation. דתניא, De-tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, beraita,
הגונב טלה מן העדר. Ha-gonev taleh min ha-eder. הגונב שה מן העדר
וסלע מן הכיס, hagonev seh min ha-eder ve-sela min ha-kis,
somebody steals a sheep from the flock or a coin from the
wallet, למקום שגנב יחזיר, le-makom she-ganav yachazir,
return it back to where you stole it from, and you're done,
you don't even have to tell the owner, דברי רבי ישמעאל. divrei
Rabbi Yishmael. That's Rabbi Yishmael says. רבי עקיבא אומר צריך דעת בעלים.
Rabbi Akiva omer tzarich da-at ba-alim. No, no, no, you have to
let the owners know. So here basically, taking it for your own
needs makes you a type of a גזלן, gazlan, we'll specify exactly
what type in a minute, okay, and so put it back anywhere
and you're done. אי רבי ישמעאל מאי איריא לא יחדו? Ei Rabbi
Yishmael mai irya lo yichdu? So according to Rabbi Yishmael, why is
it limited to the idea of... All right, you know what, no
comments. So we have, if it's according to Rabbi Yishmael, מאי איריא
לא יחדו? mai irya lo yichdu? What does it have to do
with not having a designated place? אפילו יחדו נמי, afilu yichdu nami,
even if it has a designated place, you should be allowed to
return it to the designated place and be פטור. patur. So the
גמרא Gemara says, no, לא מבעיא קאמר. lo mibaya ka-amar. The first
part of the משנה Mishnah says it goes without saying, meaning we're
ignoring the second part of the משנה, Mishnah, we're pretending as if
all we had was the first part of the משנה. Mishnah. And
when it says לא יחדו, lo yichdu, we didn't mean only לא
יחדו, lo yichdu, we really meant every case. לא מבעיא קאמר, lo
mibaya ka-amar, לא מבעיא יחדו דמקומו הוא, lo mibaya yichdu de-mkomo hu,
not only if you have a designated place and return it to
the designated place are you פטור, patur, אלא אפילו לא יחדו, ela
afilu lo yichdu, but even if you didn't have a designated place.
So what defines returning it, right? That really makes a lot of
sense. If there's no designated place and you took it to use
it for yourself, I would say you can't define it like you've
returned it now. Now you're totally a גזלן gazlan with it. So
the גמרא Gemara says, no, even in that case, אפילו לא יחדו
דלאו מקומו הוא, afilu lo yichdu delav mekomo hu, it's not like
you can as easily say you returned it. לא בעינן דעת בעלים,
lo ba-inan da-at ba-alim, once you've decided you're going to start watching
it again, not use it anymore for yourself, that's returning it. So
if you only have the רישא, reisha, you would say it's רבי
ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, and you're פטור patur because even without a specific
place, it's like you returned it. אימא סיפא, Eima seifa, now let's
look at the second part of the משנה. Mishnah. יחדו לה בעלים
מקום, Yichdu la ba-alim makom, if there is a designated place, וטלטלה
ונשברה, ve-tiltala ve-nishbera, and you moved it and it broke, בין מתוך
ידו בין משיחזרה לצרכו חייב שלא לצרכו פטור. bein mitoch yado bein
mishechazira le-tzarcho chayav she-lo le-tzarcho patur. You're חייב chayav even if you
returned it. אתאן לרבי עקיבא, Atan le-Rabbi Akiva, that's going to רבי
עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, דאמר בעינן דעת בעלים, de-amar ba-inan da-at ba-alim, that
you need the owners' knowledge, and that's why you're, you remain liable.
אי רבי עקיבא, Ei Rabbi Akiva, if it's רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva,
מאי איריא יחדו? mai irya yichdu? Why are you only, why do
you only remain liable if there's a designated place? אפילו לא יחדו
נמי, afilu lo yichdu nami, even without a designated place you remain
liable. So the גמרא Gemara again says, looking at the סיפא seifa
without the רישא, reisha, לא מבעיא קאמר, lo mibaya ka-amar, goes without
saying. לא מבעיא לא יחדו דלאו מקומו הוא, lo mibaya lo yichdu
de-lav mekomo hu, it goes without saying that if you didn't designate
a place, you cannot really return it because there's no place to
return it to. אלא אפילו יחדו נמי דמקומו הוא, ela afilu yichdu
nami de-mkomo hu, and
even if you really returned it to its right place, בעינן דעת
בעלים ba-inan da-at ba-alim you remain liable. So the גמרא Gemara says
a very reasonable thing, that with a, without a designated place it's
harder to return it, okay, and then you really have a contradiction
in the משנה. Mishnah. The beginning that has no designated place and
it's harder to return it says you're exempt, the סיפא seifa that
has a designated place and it's easier to return it says you're
חייב. chayav. So the גמרא Gemara basically says the רישא reisha is
רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael that you're exempt by returning without the owners
knowing, and the סיפא seifa is רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that you're...
I'm, that you're חייב chayav if the owners don't know, okay. That's
crazy. The משנה Mishnah seems to be distinguishing between designated and not
designated, and we're really saying that it's two very, it's two contradictory
opinions. וואו א מינוט, Woah a minute, so the גמרא Gemara says,
רישא רבי ישמעאל וסיפא רבי עקיבא? reisha Rabbi Yishmael ve-seifa Rabbi Akiva?
The beginning is רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael and the end is רבי
עקיבא? Rabbi Akiva? You're telling me this משנה Mishnah is not really
distinguishing between designated and not designated, it's really just having two contradictory
opinions? אין? In? Yes. דאמר רבי יוחנן, Damar Rabbi Yochanan, רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan said, מן דמתרגם לי חבית אליבא דחד תנא, man de-matargem
li chavit aliba de-chad tana, if you can explain to me this
משנה Mishnah of חבית chavit according to one opinion, מסבילנא מאניה בתריה
לבי מסותא, masbilna manei batrei levei masusa, I will, I will personally
bring your clothes for you to the bathhouse, okay. I'll, you know,
I'll be your attendant for the day. I'll be your attendant for
the day. Like, if you could just explain to me how to
make sense of this משנה, Mishnah, because for רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
clearly לא יחדו lo yichdu
without a designated place it's harder to return it, and the beginning
of the משנה Mishnah says that you're more exempt. Okay, now the,
the answer that the גמרא Gemara is going to say is that
the difference is that in the סיפא seifa you didn't return it
to its designated place. If you returned it to its designated place
you'd be פטור. patur. The key point missing from the end of
the משנה Mishnah is that you did not return it to the
place that it was designated. Yes.
Didn't we have in בבא בתרא Bava Batra that you couldn't use
the money that was deposited with you for other purposes? Here actually
you're doing that and then you're returning it.
Say you want to use the money. Right. Well, so what's, I
don't understand the point. But so yeah, you're not allowed to.
Well, but you're not allowed to, right?
You're not allowed to, which is why you're a גנב. ganav.
Which is you're saying if you return it to the place.
Right. You weren't allowed to, you're a גנב, ganav, and now you're
פטור patur because you're returning the money.
Okay, and then you could have used it.
No, you couldn't. If I steal something out of your wallet, okay,
was I allowed to do that?
No. Now, when I return it, do I, am I still liable
for it? No. So the fact that my liability ends doesn't mean
that I was allowed to do it. It's just at what stage
does my liability end. Right. That's practical. If I steal a sheep
from your, from your pen, was I allowed to? No. Okay, according
to רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, a day later I put it back.
Does that end my liability? Yes. Does that mean I was allowed
to do it? No.
But what was the, what was the punishment or what was...
Okay, that's a big problem we've had from the beginning, you know,
that people can steal and they don't
get... Alright, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this: Okay,
so anyway we've got this contradiction because we assume the סיפא *Seifa*
means that you returned it to its designated place and there's more
reason to be exempt in the סיפא *Seifa*. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says like this: So תרגמא *Targuma* רבי יעקב בר אבא *Rabbi
Yaakov bar Abba* קמי דרב *kamei de'Rav* שנטלה על מנת לגזלה *she-netala
al menat ligzola*. Now before we're what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s going
to do now is to actually not finish the answer. We're going
to have a couple of אמוראים *Amoraim* that are going to try
to give an answer and the key to the answer is what
I said, what I've been saying, in the סיפא *Seifa* you did
not return it to the right place and that's why you remain
liable. But before we get to that, which is the key part
of the answer, they're going to first describe why was the act
of taking it an act that gave you liability in the first
place? Why is taking it for your own purposes, what does that
make you to make you now liable for anything that's going to
go wrong until you're considered to have returned it? Okay, and we're
going to stop and figure that out and then we're going to
go back and explain that key point in the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this: Okay, תרגמא *Targuma*
רב Rav נתן בר אבא *Rav Nasan bar Abba* קמי דרב *kamei
de'Rav*. Oh I skipped a line. תרגמא *Targuma* רבי יעקב בר אבא
*Rabbi Yaakov bar Abba* קמי דרב *kamei de'Rav* שנטלה על מנת לגזלה
*she-netala al menat ligzola*.
You picked up the barrel, you figured, "I'm going to steal it".
Oh this guy left it to me, great, I'm just going to
take it, I'll use it for myself, I have some guests, we're
going to drink from it or whatever, I'm just or just whatever,
I'm just going to take it, mix it in with my barrels,
terrific. And then you had remorse. Okay, so you're a גזלן gazlan
*Gazlan*. תרגמא *Targuma* רב Rav נתן בר
אבא *Rav Nasan bar Abba* קמי דרב *kamei de'Rav* שנטלה על מנת
לשלוח בה יד *she-netala al menat lishloach bah yad*. Your intention was
not to take the whole thing for yourself, it was just to
שלוח יד *shloach yad*, which means to cast your hand against it.
What is that difference? So there are three categories here which is
important to lay out and sometimes there's a question exactly which falls
in what. To take it means I'm going to totally take it
for myself, we know what גזלן gazlan *Gazlan* is. שליחות יד shlichus
yad *shlichus yad* means I'm going to use it for myself, but
not just use as סתם *stam*. If I was going to use
it for myself, you left me a barrel and I was going
to climb on it to get something that was at the top
shelf of my, you know, whatever, that's a שואל שלא מדעת sho'el
she-lo mida'as. *Shoel she-lo mida'as*. That's not a שלוח יד *shloach yad*,
I'm simply using it, but I'm borrowing it, but I'm not borrowing
it in any way that actually is מחסר mechaser, *machsir* it. שליחות
יד shlichut yad, *shlichus yad* is an intention to use it in
a way that actually is מחסר mechaser, *machsir* it. So a classic
example is you gave me this barrel of wine, I'm not intending
to take the whole thing, but I am planning to take a
little bit from it. Okay, so I pick it up in order
to take a little bit. So I'm not a גזלן gazlan. *Gazlan*,
I'm not just a שואל sho'el? *Shoel*, I'm not just using the
barrel, I'm actually taking from it. So כעין שליחות יד shlichut yad
*k'ein shlichus yad* is an attempt to take it and not take
full possession of it but to sort of take some, use it
in a way that is מחסר mechaser *machsir* it. Okay, so those
are the three scenarios we're going to be dealing with all three.
Alright, we're going to have a later משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* about שליחות
יד shlichus yad, *shlichus yad*. What?
Gezeilah, shlichus yad and Shoel she-lo mida'as.
גזילה gezeilah, *gezeilah* is the whole thing.
גזילה gezeilah, *gezeilah* is take the whole thing for myself and not
even use it now, just take it and put it with the
rest of my barrels.
But what if it's גזילה gzeila,
*gezeilah* if I want to use some of it? It is, but
שליחות יד shlichus yad *shlichus yad* is makes you because I wanted
to use some, I'm חייב chayav *chayav* for the whole thing. Okay,
and there's an interesting question not to too much sort of tell
you what's coming up, but let's say you give me a bag
full of apples and I pick up the bag to take one
apple. Am I a שלוח יד *shloach yad* in the whole bag
or am I a גזלן gazlan *Gazlan* on one apple? But if
you've got something which is not separate units, like wine, and I
pick up the whole barrel to take a little bit of the
wine, I'm a שלוח יד *shloach yad* on the whole barrel. Alright,
is that pretty clear those differences? Alright, let's take a look. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this: Okay, so one says על
מנת לגזלה *al menat ligzola* and the other says על מנת לשלוח
בה יד *al menat lishloach bah yad*. So ובמאי קמיפלגי *v'mai kamiflegi*?
What are they debating? בשליחות יד צריך חסרון chisaron, *beshlichus yad tzarich
chisoron*. At what stage are you חייב chayav *chayav*, are you liable
for damages when you are intending to be שלוח יד *shloach yad*?
Do you actually have to remove, you know, actually be מחסר machaster
*machsir*? The context is you're intending to be מחסר machaster *machsir*, but
does it have to get to the point that you actually took
some wine out of the barrel? Or is it enough that you
picked it up with that intention? Okay, מאן דאמר *man de'amar* לגזלה
*ligzola*, the one that says that in order to make you liable
because the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* never said that you actually took the
wine out of the barrel. So the one that says you're only
liable if you plan to steal it, קסבר *kasavar* בשליחות יד צריך
חסרון chisaron. *beshlichus yad tzarich chisoron*. You wouldn't be חייב chayav *chayav*
for intending to take the wine unless you had taken some of
the wine and the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* never said that you actually
had taken and drunk some of the wine. So therefore in our
משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* the only way you're liable is if you plan
to take the whole barrel. ומאן דאמר *u'man de'amar* לשלוח בה יד
*lishloach bah yad* קסבר *kasavar* שליחות יד shlichus yad אין צריך חסרון
chisaron, *shlichus yad ein tzarich chisoron*. No, intending to take some of
the wine is enough, even if you've not taken anything, and therefore
you could be חייב chayav *chayav* on the whole thing even if
you weren't planning on stealing the whole thing, even if you were
only planning on taking a little bit of wine from it. Okay,
מתיב לה *metiv lah* רב Rav ששת *Rav Sheshes*. So now that's
why you're liable, we've still haven't explained the רישא reisha *Reisha* and
the סיפא *Seifa* of the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*. רב Rav ששת *Rav
Sheshes* challenges: מי נטלה קטני *mi netala ktani*? The משנה *Mishnah* doesn't
say you were נטלה *netala*, which means like you picked it up.
Okay, because whether to be a גזלן gazlan *Gazlan*, we already know
from בבא קמא *Bava Kamma*, to be a גזלן gazlan *Gazlan* you
have to do an act... act of a קנין. kinyan. So you'd
only be חייב chayav if you lifted up the barrel. Also שליחות
יד shlichus yad. is also, you're only חייב chayav. if you do
an act of a קנין. kinyan If I go to Michael's barrel
of wine that's sitting in my room in my thing and I
turn on the spout and I get a glass from it and
I drink the glass, I am a גזלן gazlan, on that glass.
By the way, if you want a fourth scenario, if I turn
the spout and I let it spit, I'm a מזיק mazik on
the wine. If I take a turn the spout and I take
a glass I'm a גזלן gazlan. on that glass, but I'm not
a שולח יד sholeyach yad on the whole ba- on the barrel.
For me to be a שולח יד sholeyach yad on the whole
barrel, it's like גזילה, I have to pick up the whole barrel
with the intent to use some of the wine. Okay, so picking
up the whole barrel to take it is a גזלן. gazlan. Picking
up the whole barrel, doing a קנין kinyan. with the int- dragging
would not count. It's not a מעשה קנין. maaseh kinyan. Picking up
the whole barrel with the intent to use some of the wine
is a שולח יד. sholeyach yad. And then the question is, so
I have to actually use the wine to be liable or just
intending to do it? All right, so therefore I can't be a
גזלן gazlan and I can't be a שולח יד sholeyach yad if
I didn't pick it up. So what am I? So he says,
מידי נטלה קתני, midei natla katani, doesn't say you picked it up.
טלטלה קתני, tiltala katani, you moved it. אלא אמר רב ששת הכא
במאי עסקינן כגון שטלטלה להביא עליה גוזלות. ela amar Rav Sheshet hacha
be-mai askinan kigon she-tiltala lehavi aleha gozalot. You moved it in order
to get some pigeons, meaning you basically you moved it over to
your bookshelf in order to get some books that's on a high
place in your bookshelf. You moved it as a ladder. So you're
not- you're not a גזלן gazlan, because you didn't do a מעשה
קנין, maaseh kinyan, you're not a שולח יד sholeyach yad because you
didn't do a מעשה קנין. maaseh kinyan. What you are is a
שואל שלא מדעת. sho'el she-lo mida'as You are using somebody's object without
their permission and therefore you're liable. Either now there's a debate, is
שואל שלא מדעת sho'el she-lo mida'as a גזלן gazlan or a שואל?
sho'el, But even if you're only- we're going to say גזלן, gazlan
but even if you're only a שואל, sho'el a שואל sho'el is
liable for damages and a שואל sho'el is liable for אונס, ones,
right, a שואל sho'el. is liable for anything that happens. Okay, but
the גמרא Gemara is going to say גזלן. gazlan One minute. דקסבר
שואל שלא מדעת גזלן הוי. dekasavar sho'el she-lo mida'as gazlan havei. And
it's of the opinion that a שואל שלא מדעת sho'el she-lo mida'as
is a type of a גזלן. gazlan. And therefore, you know, you're
fully liable until you return it and then it's like you stole
the object and now you returned it to its original place and
now you are exempt. Okay, and now that we've got three possibilities
of in the משנה why taking it makes you liable. You're either
a גזלן gazlan. in some scenarios, you're a שולח יד sholeyach yad
in other types of scenarios, and you're a- and a שואל שלא
מדעת sho'el she-lo mida'as. in yet a third type of scenario. But
one of those cases you are liable and now the question is
when do you get exempt? And here's how the משנה reads. וכולה
רבי ישמעאל היא, vekula Rabbi Yishmael hi, the entire משנה is רבי
ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. וסיפא ve-seifa so we know why in the רישא
you're פטור, patur, you returned it, okay, you don't need דעת בעלים.
da'as ba'alim. וסיפא ve-seifa so why are you חייב chayav in the
end? שהניחה במקום שאינה מקומה. shenicha bemakom she-einam mekoma. When it says
you're ex- you're- I mean, why are you חייב chayav. in the
end? Because you returned it not to its designated place. Yes, with
a designated place it's easier to be פטור patur if you returned
it to the right place. But the reason in the משנה it
says with a designated place you're חייב chayav? is it's a scenario
that you did not return it to the designated place. רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan now why would רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan not accept that
answer? It's a good way of answering it.
Why didn't- did רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan now go ahead and take
the, you know, the clothes of whoever it was for the bathhouse,
did he buy that answer? No, he did not buy that answer.
So he says, הניחה במקומו משמע. henicha bimkomo mashma. When it says
you put it back, you put it down, presumably it means in
the place you took it from. So the משנה does not make
sense because he assumes you put it back in the same place
and then there's more reason to be exempt when it has a
designated place than when it doesn't. But that's the פשט pshat of
the משנה when is it considered like you've returned it and your
liability ended. But this now is opening up for us what, you
know, an earlier question which to some- I mean, they're both interesting
conceptual questions, but the question about when does your liability begin, what
type of act makes you a גזלן, gazlan, a שולח יד, sholeyach
yad, you know, or שואל שלא מדעת. sho'el she-lo mida'as Yes.
I just want to make sure I understand this. Let's say you
mean- forget about a barrel of wine, all right, a cow. Your
cow, I'm watching your cow, I don't move it, I go over
and I milk it. Right, so what am I now?
Well, you're a גזלן gazlan, on the milk.
Are you a- are you a- you're not a שולח יד sholeyach
yad and you're not a גזלן gazlan, on the cow. Are you
a שואל שלא מדעת sho'el she-lo mida'as on the cow? You might
be, although we'll see about- I'll say something about that in a
minute. Okay? So- but you're certainly not a גזלן gazlan or a
שולח יד. sholeyach yad. All right, exactly when you'd become a שואל
שלא מדעת sho'el she-lo mida'as. is a good question because right why
are you- you know, so I'm going to address that in a
minute, it's going to come up. Yes.
You want to שומר shomer and you moved the barrel to climb
on top of it. Yes.
No, the act of moving it to climb on top of it
makes you a שואל שלא מדעת. sho'el she-lo mida'as You are borrowing
it without permission. Okay, so you borrow my thing without permission, you're
liable.
Doesn't necessarily need to be the case that you're a שומר shomer
for the object.
Correct. Correct. You just come into this room and you take this
chair and you go ahead and you use it and it breaks,
you were שואל שלא מדעת sho'el she-lo mida'as. and you're liable.
What if I return it, I'm okay?
Right. Yeah, but if I go down to the kitchen and take
someone else's mug and pour myself a cup of coffee.
Yeah, you also שואל שלא מדעת.
shoel she-lo mi-daat, But you said that's not a- I'm not a
גזלן.
gazlan Correct, did you plan on keeping the mug? No. So then
you're not a גזלן. Okay, right. Okay. All right, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay. Now... Now איתמר, itmar, רב ולוי. Rav v'Levi. Now we get
to discuss this issue. Okay, debate of רב Rav and לוי. Levi.
חד אמר שליחות יד צריכה חסרון וחד אמר שליחות יד אינה צריכה
חסרון. Chad amar shlichut yad tzericha chisaron ve-chad amar shlichut yad einah
tzericha chisaron. Using something, again, with the intent somehow to take from
it, okay, not to take the whole thing but to take from
it, שליחות יד, shlichus yad do you actually need to take from
it in order to be liable or just the taking with that
intent makes you? Okay, now by the way, שליחות יד shlichus yad
is a concept only by שומרים, shomrim, to get back to you.
גזילה, מזיק, mazik, שואל שלא מדעת, shoel she-lo mi-daat? that could be
by objects, whether you know, whether you have a prior relationship to
the object or not. שולח יד sholeiach yad is a violation, is
a specific liability of a שומר shomer and a violation of your
liability as a שומר. shomer. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this.
So רב ולוי, Rav v'Levi, חד אמר שליחות יד צריכה חסרון, chad
amar shlichut yad tzericha chisaron, you're only fully liable for the object
when you were actually מחסר, mechasser intent is not enough. וחד אמר
שליחות יד אינה צריכה חסרון, ve-chad amar shlichut yad einah tzericha chisaron,
it's not required. תסתיים דרב הוא דאמר שליחות יד אינה צריכה חסרון,
Tistayeim d'Rav hu d'amar shlichut yad einah tzericha chisaron, רב Rav is
the one who, let's conclude that רב is the one who says
that even without being מחסר, mechasser you're liable. דתניא, d'tanya, we learned
in a ברייתא: Beraita: רועה שהיה רואה את עדרו, Ro'eh she-hayah ro'eh
et edro,
he was watching a כדרך הרואה את עדרו, k'derech ha-ro'eh et edro,
right, a shepherd was watching his flock. והניח עדרו, v'hinniach edro, and
he left it, left it, ובא לעיר, u-va l'ir, and he went
to the town, came to the town. ובא
זאב וטרף ובא ארי ודרס, U-va ze'ev v'taraf u-va ari v'daras, and
a wolf came and tore the animals or a lion came and
consumed them. You know the difference between טרף taraf is that it
kills it and takes it away as opposed to a lion that
presumably kills it and eats it there. Anyway, פטור, patur, he's exempt.
Now why is he פטור? patur? What do you mean, he abandoned
the flock? So the basic point that a different גמרא Gemara is
going to say, which is not our interest right now, is he
went back during when it was break time. Okay? So if there
was a standard break time that's accepted amongst shepherds, at noon you're
allowed to go, you know, go into the town and get yourself
some lunch and come back and that's when it happened and he's
not liable for going and getting lunch during lunchtime. Fine,
that's not our interest. Our interest is the next part. הניח מקלו
ותרמילו עליה. Hinniach maklo v'tarmilo aleha. Let's say he left his staff
and his pouch on it. Okay, חייב. chayav? He's חייב chayav. because
leaving his pouch on the animal makes him to some degree something
on the animal: a גזלן, a שולח יד, sholeiach yad, something. Okay,
because he was using the animal for his usage, right? Now the
most obvious thing to say is if I asked you which of
those categories would you put that in? גזלן, שולח יד, sholeiach yad,
or
שואל שלא מדעת? shoel she-lo mi-daat, Putting your staff and your pouch
on the animal, what? שואל שלא מדעת, shoel she-lo mi-daat right? You
don't want to take it for yourself, you were just using it.
It's like using the bale to stand on. The funny thing here
is the גמרא Gemara completely ignores that possibility, which is the simplest
read.
Well, so close. So רש״י Rashi has some funny explanation that you
can't be a שואל שלא מדעת shoel she-lo mi-daat on animals. Nobody
really understands what רש״י Rashi is talking about. הרמב״ן ha-Ramban says what
James said to some degree. He said to be a שואל שלא
מדעת shoel she-lo mi-daat I have to to some degree pervert it
from its natural path. Like in this case, he says the sheep
is still there with all the other sheep, it's going out, it's
grazing, I have not somehow taken it away from the owner in
any sense of the word. It's totally doing what it's supposed to
be doing right now. Okay? So if there's a concern that I
might be מחסר mechaser it, that maybe is a different story, right?
Let's say your chair was right
there and you brought your chair into my room, it was right
there and I needed to stand on it to reach something from
the top. Right? Would I be a שואל שלא מדעת shoel she-lo
mi-daat if I just sat on it? To be a שואל שלא
מדעת shoel she-lo mi-daat. to be liable requires to some degree taking
it away from where it's supposed to be. Okay, so that's sort
of like the issue that הרמב״ן ha-Ramban raises. It could be that
if there's a concern that I was damaged, I might damage it,
maybe it might. Anyway, so for some reason we are ignoring שואל
שלא מדעת. shoel she-lo mi-daat, That's what הרמב״ן ha-Ramban says. I did
not somehow take it away from the owner in any meaningful way.
Okay, so we don't know then why I'm חייב. chayav. So let's
take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says: וחייב, הוינא בה משום
דהניח מקלו ותרמילו עליה חייב? V'chayav, havina bah mishum d'hinniach maklo v'tarmilo
aleha chayav? Just because you put your staff on it you're חייב?
chayav. הא שקלינהו! Ha shaklinhu! Presumably after you put it on, you
removed it. So isn't that sort of like whatever you were, a
גזלן, a שולח יד, sholeiach yad, makes maybe it's like returning it
to the owners? And anyway, what were you to begin with? So
אמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה אמר רב, בעודן עליה. Amar
Rav Nachman amar Rabbah bar Avuha amar Rav, b'oden aleha. No, you
didn't return it, they're still on it. You left it on it
while you went to town to get lunch, you left your staff
on it. Okay, still, what does that make you? וכי עודן עליה
מאי הוי? V'chi oden aleha mai havai? So what? Big deal. The
גמרא Gemara assumes that you're not because remember, if we no longer
have the option of
שואל שלא מדעת, shoel she-lo mi-daat, the only thing you could be
is a גזלן or a שולח יד. sholeiach yad. Now what did
I tell you you needed to do to be a גזלן or
a שולח יד? sholeiach yad? You needed to do a קנין. kinyan.
You needed to pick it up. Okay? Putting your staff on it
is not a קנין. kinyan All right? So the best answer would
have been שואל שלא מדעת, sho'el shelo mada'at. but for some reason
as we said, that's not an option. So you have to now
have done a מעשה קנין. ma'aseh kinyan. So therefore we're still, why
are you חייב?
chayav Because שליחות... shlichut... שליחות יד גזל דזו חסרה, shlichut yad gazal
dezo chissora, right?
Well, that's a separate issue, but we can't even get off the
ground until there's
a מעשה קניין. ma'aseh kinyan. Okay, וכי אדם לעולם יחייב המשיכה? vechi
adam l'olam yechayev hamishicha? You didn't draw it, you didn't do a
מעשה קניין. ma'aseh kinyan. If our only option here is שליחות יד,
shelichus yad אמר רב שמואל בר רב יצחק אמר רב שהכישה במקל
ורצה לפניו. Amar Rav Shmuel Bar Rav Yitzchak Amar Rav shehikisha bemakal
veratza lefano. Yeah, so he did hit it in order to that
you were saying somehow the idea of it's conceptually שליחות יד shelichus
yad is you're making use. What's your use? You're going to take
it to put your staff on it. In order to take it
to put your staff on it, I don't know, you hit it,
it's like a funny thing to run in order that therefore now
it'll be next to you so you can put your staff on
it. Okay. הכישה, Hehikisha, right?
Yeah, so that's an interesting thing. Isn't a shepherd generally like leading
his sheep? But I guess when they're out grazing, a
shepherd leads from behind.
Yeah, so I was wondering that too.
Somehow you drew it towards you, you hit it towards you so
now you can put your stuff on it. That's somehow the idea.
וכי Vechi so, so you're שליח יד sholeiach yad to use it.
You're taking it to use it.
Okay, so so the גמרא Gemara says, ורצה לפניו. veratza lefano. והלא
חסרה? V'halo chasra? There's no חיסרון. chisaron. So you're שליח יד sholeiach
yad without חיסרון chisaron and you're חייב. chayav אלא שמע מינה קסבר
שליחות יד אינה צריכה חיסרון. Ella Shma Mina Kasavar Shlichus Yad Einah
Tzericha Chisaron. So you see since רב gave that answer, so we
cheated this very complicated case to be a שליחות יד shelichus yad
and with a מעשה קניין, ma'aseh kinyan, but there's no חיסרון. chisaron.
So you see רב doesn't need חיסרון chisaron for שליחות יד. shelichus
yad So the גמרא
says משיכה meshicha by the way, what kind of קניין? kinyan? משיכה?
Meshicha? You don't have to pick it up.
Oh, so I didn't mean lift up, you have to do a
מעשה קניין. ma'aseh kinyan. No, no, you have to do a מעשה
קניין, ma'aseh kinyan, right. אימא שהכישה... Eima shehikisha... so the גמרא says,
oh, אימא שהכישה במקל. Eima shehikisha bemakal. No, not necessarily. Maybe that
there was a חיסרון. chisaron. Maybe he gave it a good hit
with the, you know, the thing, so that tiny little חיסרון chisaron
that I don't know got a bruise or something, that's considered a
חיסרון. chisaron. דיקא נמי דקתני שהכישה במקל. Dika nami diktanei shehikisha bemakal.
Why did it say that you hit it? Why didn't it just
say that you know, you let it, you know, you verbally let
it or something like that? שמע מינה, Shma mina, which is a
pretty bad deal, but okay. So the גמרא says, תוספות Tosafot says
very often when we talk about משיכה meshicha we talk about hitting
it, it's not to make a point about חיסרון. chisaron. So this
is conceptually very hard because again, a classic שליחות יד shelichus yad
is I'm using something and I'm going to, planning on taking the
little something away. Here, you know, and the question is do I
actually have to take it or not? Here, even if I did
a מעשה קניין, ma'aseh kinyan, I drew it towards me, it's not
to keep it, it's in order to make use of it. Okay,
but in order to make use of it with a, again, what's
the exact thing I'm taking from you? Meaning the natural way to
think about this is again like a שואל שלא מדעת. sho'el shelo
mada'at What am I taking from you? But it would be an
interesting case of let's say when you use something you slightly damage
it. Okay, so that would be the question of is that a
type of when I take the wine the way I'm מחסר mechaser
it and I'm a שליח יד sholeiach yad is I have a
whole barrel I'm taking a little wine. But let's say instead I've
got I don't know what would be a good example of something...
let's say you take it to use it.
Right, right. I took I took your brand new shoes, okay, you
know, they have no scuff marks on the bottom or whatever, right,
and I just put them on to just do a, to walk
across the street. Okay, that would be another case of a חיסרון.
chisaron. Okay, so the little damage that everything gets a little worn,
you know, a little bit, the car, yeah I know.
Anyway, so that so that would be a similar scenario of שליחות
יד shlichut yad and does it actually have to be used in
a way which causes the חיסרון? chisaron? So here too, the animal
got a little bit hit, that was a little חיסרון. chisaron. But
again, in most of those scenarios, you're going to say you're going
to be a שואל שלא מדעת sho'el shelo mada'at. before you're מחסר
it. Which is why the רמב"ן Ramban has to figure out why
in this particular scenario it didn't pervert from its normal sort of
you know location enough to be
a
שואל שלא מדעת. shoel she'lo m'daat.
It's
just
like this: ומידי דרב סבר שליחות יד צריכה חסרון, U'mid'Rav savar shelichus
yad tzericha chisaron, since רב says
it
requires, לוי סבר שליחות יד אינה צריכה חסרון. Levi savar shelichus yad
einah tzericha chisaron. It doesn't. מאי טעמא דלוי? Mai ta'ama d'Levi? What's
the reason of
לוי? Levi? אמר רבי יוחנן
משום רבי יוסי בן נהוראי, Amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Yose ben
Nehorai, meaning presumably the
phrase שליחות יד shlichut yad seems to be some sense of actually
incursion into it. It would suggest חסרון, chisaron. not just suggest an
intention. So what's the reason of לוי? Levi? So he has to
be, he has to be defended, is the opinion that it doesn't
require חסרון. chisaron. So what's that logic? Okay, so he says, and
now we're going to spend the rest of the time really looking
at the פסוקים. psukim. אמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי יוסי בן נהוראי,
Amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Yose ben Nehorai, משום שליחות יד האמורה
בשומר שכר משליחות יד האמורה בשומר חנם. mishum shelichus yad ha'amurah b'shomer
sachar mishlichus yad ha'amurah b'shomer chinam. That it basically is like, you
know, repeated or
it's different. The שמה shama it says by both שומר שכר shomer
sachar and by שומר חנם shomer chinam it says that you take
an oath ונקרב בעל הבית אל האלהים אם לא שלח ידו במלאכת
רעהו. v'nikrav ba'al habayis el ha'elohim im lo shalach yado b'mleches re'ehu.
Okay, that you take an oath basically, you come to court to
clarify that you were not שולח יד. shole'ach yad. And it says
it both by a שומר חנם shomer chinam and by a שומר
שכר shomer sachar in the תורה. Torah. And it says they're different.
Now what by different means is it means somehow that you know
it said it a second time and therefore the second time is
to tell you you don't need a חסרון, chisaron, okay?
So the first one you needed it to tell me, but the
second one you didn't. The second one was different than the first,
and the only thing it's doing there is to tell you you
don't need a חסרון. chisaron. So let's take a look. The גמרא
will spell that out. ואני אומר, v'ani omer, I say אינה משונה.
einah meshunah.
No, it's not different, they both are needed. Okay, מאי משונה? mai
meshunah? What does it mean it's different? לא תימא שליחות יד בשומר
שכר, Lo teima shelichus yad b'shomer sachar,
the Torah didn't have to say it by a
שומר שכר. shomer sachar. תיתי משומר חנם, Teisi mishomer chinam, I could
have learned it out from שומר חנם. shomer chinam. ומה שומר חנם
שפטור בגניבה ואבידה, U'mah shomer chinam shepatur b'gneivah va'aveidah, a שומר חנם
shomer chinam has a low level of liability, he's exempt if it
gets stolen or lost, שלח יד חייב, shalach yad chayav, and the
Torah says that if he שלח יד shalach yad he's liable. So
שומר שכר שחייב בגניבה ואבידה, shomer sachar shechayav b'gneivah va'aveidah, שומר שכר
shomer sachar whose liability starts off as higher, okay, לא כל שכן,
lo kol shekein, certainly if he שלח יד shalach yad he'd be
חייב. chayav למה הלכתא כתביה רחמנא, L'mai hilchasa kasveih Rachmana,
why did the Torah then also write שליחות יד shlichut yad. by
שומר שכר? shomer sachar? למימרא לך L'meimra lach I'll tell you, שליחות
יד אינה צריכה חסרון, shelichus yad einah tzericha chisaron, that there's a
second category that שליחות יד shlichut yad is even broader than you
would have imagined, it doesn't even, you don't even need to be
מחסר to take anything away from the object. That's his opinion. ואני
אומר, v'ani omer, and I say אינה משונה, einah meshunah, it's no
different. כרבי אלעזר דאמר דבר זה אחד היא, k'Rabbi Elazar d'amar davar
zeh achad hi, it's all one. מאי דבר זה אחד היא? Mai
davar zeh achad hi? What does it mean it's all one? Which
is funny, it's all one really means but each one is sort
of necessary is they're doing the same point. They're not coming to
add a new idea, oh, even without חסרון. chisaron? They're all coming
to tell you the basic same point that שליחות יד shlichut yad
is חייב. chayav, But you need to tell me both in the
case of שומר חנם shomer chinam and in the case of שומר
שכר. shomer sachar. משום דאיכא למפרך, Mishum d'ika l'mifrach,
you couldn't just tell me שומר חנם shomer chinam because you could
have challenged and said just because you're חייב chayav. by שומר חנם
shomer chinam you're not חייב chayav, by שומר שכר. shomer sachar. Why?
Isn't שומר חנם shomer chinam a lower level of liability? No, here's
what I would have said. מה לשומר חנם שכן משלם כפל בטוען
טענת גנב, Mah l'shomer chinam shekein m'shalem kefel b'to'ein ta'anas ganav,
שומר חנם shomer chinam has an area of liability higher than a
שומר שכר shomer sachar really. What is that? Well, if a שומר
חנם shomer chinam says it was נגנב nignav and he takes an
oath and it turns out that he was the one who stole
it, he pays כפל, kefel, right? People remember that? So that will
never happen by a שומר שכר. shomer sachar. Why will it never
happen by a שומר שכר? shomer sachar? Because if a שומר שכר
shomer sachar says נגנב, nignav, he has to pay the principal. So
but there is one case that a שומר חנם shomer chinam will
have a worse punishment than a שומר שכר, shomer sachar, pay כפל
kefel which will never happen by a שומר שכר. shomer sachar. So
therefore since that is a case that he has a worse, that
he can have a higher liability, you can't learn out from שומר
חנם shomer chinam to שומר שכר. shomer sachar. Okay? ומאן דלא פרך,
U'man d'lo parach,
the one who says no no no of course you can learn
out from שומר חנם shomer chinam to שומר שכר, shomer sachar, סבר
קרנא בלא שבועה עדיפא מכפילא בשבועה, savar karna b'lo shvuah adifa mi'kfila
b'shvuah,
which makes a lot of sense. The principal that you have to
pay and you can't take an oath, which is the הלכה halacha
of a שומר שכר shomer sachar who says נגנב, nignav, is a
weightier liability than the risk of paying כפל kefel for a false
oath for a שומר חנם. shomer chinam. Another way of saying it
is the only reason a שומר חנם shomer chinam pays כפל kefel
is it starts from a fundamentally lower liability than a שומר שכר.
shomer sachar. Because he's exempt for גניבה, gneivah, there's a way that
it could ultimately lead to him paying כפל. kefel. Okay, so anyway
that's the question: can you say that anything by שומר חנם shomer
chinam you can learn out קל וחומר kal v'chomer by שומר שכר,
shomer sachar, or do you say since a שומר חנם shomer chinam
because of his low liability sometimes pays
כפל, kefel, you can't learn out from שומר חנם shomer chinam to
שומר שכר shomer sachar and it has to say it in both
places. So if you say that you couldn't have learned it out,
the repetition by שומר שכר shomer sachar is to tell you you're
חייב chayav? even if you did not actually מחסר it. Okay, we
might have to take two or more minutes today but we're getting
to the end of the דף. daf. Okay, so the גמרא says
like this.
רבא אמר, Rava amar, now רבא Rava says, לא תימא שליחות יד
לא בשומר חנם ולא בשומר שכר. lo teima shelichus yad lo b'shomer
chinam v'lo b'shomer sachar. You know what, the Torah didn't have to
say it either in שומר חנם shomer chinam or in
שומר שכר. shomer sachar. תיתי משואל, Teisi misho'el, just figure out שליחות
יד shlichut yad from an analogy to a שואל. shoel? Okay, what's
the analogy?
What's the הלכה halacha if you're a שואל? shoel A שואל shoel.
is חייב באונס, chayav b'ones, liable for anything that happens. That's when
you're using it with my permission. שולח יד sholach yad when you
go ahead to take it for your own purposes, okay, then so
you should at least be like a שואל. shoel A שואל shoel,
is שולח יד sholach yad with permission. He's using it with permission.
You're using it without permission, so חייב, chayav. of course you should
be חייב. chayav Now of course there's a little bit of a
difference, right? Because I would... we just got through here beforehand distinguishing
between שליחות יד shlichut yad and שואל שלא מדעת. shoel she'lo m'daat,
Right? If you're שולח יד, sholach yad, you're only planning on taking
a little bit of the wine, you're not sort of like using
the whole wine or whatever, it's not exactly the same. But still
the point there is, if when you have a right to use
it and borrow it, you're fully liable, when you're using it without
permission, whatever form you're using it, as a שואל, shoel, as a
שולח יד, sholach yad, certainly you should be liable, yes.
When I'm a שואל, shoel. I'm not allowed to destroy part of
it.
Right. So all the more reason that when you are destroying you
should be liable. So that's the point, it's a קל וחומר kal
v'chomer by analogy to a שואל. shoel Okay. So therefore
ושולח יד... v'sholach yad... so a שואל shoel who uses it with
permission is חייב, שומר חנם ושומר שכר לא כל שכן? shomer chinam
v'shomer sachar lo kol she'ken? So certainly if you're supposed to be
watching it and instead you make use of it for yourself as
you know, then certainly, and especially you used it with actually taking
something away, of course you should be liable. So למה נאמרה? lama
ne'emra? So why did the Torah have to therefore tell me that
a שולח יד sholach yad is חייב? Of course you are. חד
למימר לך chad l'meimar lach שליחות יד אין צריכה חסרון, shlichut yad
ein tzricha chisaron, must be to want tell me that even with
even just intending to use it, even before you got around using
it, you're already חייב. ואידך, v'idach, and the other thing... so why
does it... so or that's why what tell me twice? שלא תאמר
דיו לבוא מן הדין להיות כנדון. she'lo tomar dai lo lavin hadin
l'hiot k'nidon.
Don't say, oh we'll just limit it to the analogy of a
שואל shoel. and don't go beyond שואל. shoel ומה שואל בבעלים פטור...
u'ma shoel b'baalim patur... by a שואל shoel, there's a special הלכה
halacha בעליו עמו לא ישלם. ba'alav imo lo yeshalem.
If you're in my employ while I'm borrowing your object and something
happens to your object, then I'm exempt. So maybe let's say you're...
I'm employing you and I was שולח יד sholach yad in your
פקדון. pikadon. So if we only know שליחות יד shlichut yad by
analogy to a שואל, shoel well שואל shoel, in that scenario would
be exempt. So don't think that the owner's being employed by the
שומר shomer would make the שומר shomer exempt by שליחות יד. shlichut
yad, So therefore we had to say that it really is a
separate category. So אף שומר חנם ושומר שכר בבעלים פטור... af shomer
chinam v'shomer sachar b'baalim patur... so you shouldn't say that it says
it twice. Okay. So Rava is saying you could learn it out
by analogy by שואל, shoel. and it says it twice, once by
שומר חנם shomer chinam and once by שומר שכר shomer sachar to
tell you number one, you don't actually have to take anything away,
just having the intention is enough, you don't need חסרון, and number
two, that בעלים baalim doesn't make a difference. ולמאן דאמר u'l'man d'amar
שליחות יד צריכה חסרון, shlichut yad tzricha chisaron, now if you say
that by שולח יד sholach yad you actually have to take something
away, so הני תרתי שליחות יד למה לי? hani tartei shlichut yad
lama li? Why did it have to tell me both by שומר
שכר shomer sachar and שומר חנם? shomer chinam? Just learn it out
by analogy from a שואל. shoel, חדא chada שלא תאמר דיו לבוא
מן הדין להיות כנדון. she'lo tomar dai lo lavin hadin l'hiot k'nidon.
One we already said, to tell me don't think if you're basing
it on analogy of a שואל, shoel. don't think if the owners
are employed by you that somehow means you're off the hook. ואידך,
v'idach, and the second one, because isn't... not to tell you you
don't need to be מחסר because this is the opinion that says
you're only חייב if you actually do take something from it. So
what's the second reason... the second time it says שליחות יד in
the Torah? כדתניא: k'di t'anya:
ונקרב בעל הבית אל האלהים
אם לא שלח ידו במלאכת רעהו. v'nikrav ba'al habayit el ha'elohim im
lo shalach yado b'mlechet re'ehu. So what does that mean? You come
to the judges that you did not שולח יד? sholach yad? So
it means לשבועה, l'shvua, right, you have to take an oath what
happened to it and that you were not שולח יד. sholach yad.
אתה אומר לשבועה אינו אלא לדין? ata omer l'shvua eino ela l'din?
Maybe it means that you actually just have a judgment case about
that but you don't actually have to take an oath about it.
נאמר שליחות יד למטה ונאמר שליחות יד למעלה. ne'emar shlichut yad l'mata
v'ne'emar shlichut yad l'mala. No, it says שליחות יד in two places,
שומר חנם shomer chinam and שומר שכר. shomer sachar. מה להלן לשבועה,
ma halan l'shvua, in one place the Torah is explicitly that you
do take an oath, אף כאן לשבועה, af kan l'shvua, here too
you take an oath. So the reason it says it twice is
to make it clear that it's through an oath and not just
through a court case. Okay, so bottom line is that שליחות יד
it said twice in the Torah. You could have said once and
I could have learned it out or I could have learned it
out by analogy to a שואל. shoel The reason to repeat it
is maybe to tell me even without חסרון. So that's the core
debate, does שליחות יד require חסרון? And then there's these other issues
that even with בעלים baalim you're still going to be liable and
that the שליחות יד has to be clarified through a שבועה, shvua,
not just through a court case. But bottom line, the important thing
to take away is these three concepts. גזילה, taking it, doing a
מעשה קנין ma'aseh kinyan with the intent to keep it all to
yourself. שליחות יד, which is doing an act that would constitute an
act of קנין but you're not trying to keep it all for
yourself, you're just trying to use it in a way that's going
to be מחסר it. Take some wine, use an object that's going
to cause some type of wear and tear. And the question is
you actually have to use it or just take it with that
intent? And then the third case is a שואל שלא מדעת, that
you actually do use something and you're seen as a שואל and
that also leads to a liability. Okay, well okay, we continue in
the משנה *Mishnah*. So the משנה *Mishnah* says המפקיד מעות אצל חברו
*Hamaphkid maot etzel chaveiro*. I give money to someone, צררן והפשילן לאחוריו
*tziraran vehifshilan
leachorav*. He bundled them and he swung them behind his back, or
he gave them to his little son or daughter, or he locked
the door before them and it wasn't locked properly, and then they
were stolen, they were lost, he's basically liable for them because he
didn't watch it like a proper guard. השומרים *Hashomrim* have a certain
way that they have to watch money and this is not it.
It's actually kind of interesting if you think about it today. He
swung it behind his back? I think if you go on the
train or a bus, you might put your backpack on your front,
not on your back, because when it's behind your back, that's like
considered you're not guarding it well. But we continue, so the גמרא
*Gemara* says, okay what is the גמרא *Gemara* gonna talk about? It's
gonna look at this phrase המפקיד מעות אצל חברו *Hamaphkid maot etzel
chaveiro*.